Henderson mss., 1975-2006 LMC 2511
Lilly Library
Henderson mss.
1975-2006
Lilly Library
Henderson, Bill, 1941-
LMC 2511
6 Boxes 6 standard
The Henderson mss., 1975-2005, consists primarily of the papers and manuscripts of author and editor Bill Henderson, who founded the Pushcart Press and the Pushcart Prize.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Biographical Note
Born April 5, 1941 in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, William Charles Henderson attended Hamilton College and pursued graduate studies briefly at both Harvard and the University of Pennsylvania. He and his uncle Howard Galloway started the small publishing house Nautilus Books in 1970, which then published Henderson's first novel The Galapagos Kid under the pseudonym Luke Walton. Neither the novel nor the publishing house proved successful.
In 1973 Henderson launched the Pushcart Press with The Publish it Yourself Handbook-Literary Tradition and How-To Without Commercial or Vanity Publishers, compiled and edited by him. The handbook was not only successful but has seen several reprintings over the years. He started the Pushcart Prize series in 1976. This annual anthology that celebrates small presses and little magazines and their writers has continued without interruption. In 1982 Henderson started the Editors' Book Award for overlooked manuscripts. In this program he asks editors at commercial houses to nominate manuscripts they were not able to publish because of financial pressure. He then chooses one from these nominations and publishes it by Pushcart Press.
Over the years several selections published in this series have been reprinted in mass market and trade paperback editions, occasionally by the very commercial house that had rejected them the first time around. In addition to his editing and publishing work, Henderson has also written several volumes of memoirs, essays and book reviews for the New York Times, Publishers Weekly and elsewhere, and has been a visiting lecturer at several colleges and summer writing programs.
Arrangement/Organization
The collection is organized into the following series: I. Correspondence; II. Pushcart; III. Writings; and IV. Additions.
Scope and Content Note
Consist primarily of the papers and manuscripts of author and editor Bill Henderson. The correspondence from authors, editors and poets is primarily concerned with letters of nomination for the Pushcart Prize anthologies. Series II consists primarily of form letters, clippings of reviews and ads, and printed brochures and announcements relating to the Pushcart Prize, as well as materials regarding the trademark registration of the pushcart, a history of the Pushcart Press, The Editors' Book Award, and reviews and articles about the Press. Series III consists of manuscripts, correspondence and reviews, etc. of writings and works written, edited, or published by Bill Henderson.
Acquisition Information
Purchase; 2005.
Pushcart Prize.; Pushcart Editor's Book Award.; Little magazines.; Private presses.; Publishers and publishing; Pushcart Press.; Henderson, Bill, 1941- --Correspondence.
- Correspondence (Box 1)
  - General correspondence, (21 folders). (Box 1)
    General
    Arranged alphabetically
    - Abish, Walter (Box 1)
    - Ashbery, John (Box 1)
    - Bass, Rick (Box 1)
    - Booth, Philip (Box 1)
    - Bowles, Paul (Box 1)
    - Bukowski, Charles (Box 1)
    - Carruth, Hayden (Box 1)
    - Carver, Raymond (Box 1)
    - Gallagher, Tess (Box 1)
    - Grumbach, Doris (Box 1)
    - Hoagland, Edward (Box 1)
    - Irving, John (Box 1)
    - Kizer, Carolyn (Box 1)
    - Nin, Anais (Box 1)
    - Oats, Joyce Carol (Box 1)
    - Plimpton, George (Box 1)
    - Stafford, William (Box 1)
    - Wilentz, Theodore (Box 1)
  - Pushcart Prize correspondence and nominations, 1975-1982; (14 folders) (Box 1)
  - Pushcart Prize correspondence and nominations, 1983-1992; (23 folders) (Box 2)
  - Pushcart Prize correspondence and nominations, 1993-2000; (27 folders) (Box 3)
  - Pushcart Prize correspondence and nominations undated A-Z, 2001-2005; (17 folders) (Box 4)
- Pushcart
  Scope and Contents
  Miscellaneous files concerning the Pushcart Prize and Pushcart Press
  - Pushcart Prize (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous notes and fragments concerning Pushcart Prize and nominations, etc. (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Form letters to authors, 1975-2005 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Form letters to editors concerning nominations, 1976-2005 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Clippings: ads and reviews (Box 4, Folder 21-22)
    - Press releases (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Pushcart Press (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - History (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Miscellaneous. (Box 4, Folder 25)
      Includes materials concerning trademark registration of Pushcart
    - The Editors' Book Award (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Clippings concerning Pushcart Press and Bill Henderson (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Printed (Box 4, Folder 28)
- Writings
  Writings and works written, edited, or published by Bill Henderson. Arranged alphabetically by title after the biographical materials.
  - Biographical materials (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - The Art of Literary Publishing: Editors on Their Craft, edited by Bill Henderson (Yonkers, NY: Pushcart Press, )., 1980; October 27, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 2-4)
    Photocopy of T.D. with corrections and changes in black ink. October 27, 1979.
  - The Art of Literary Publishing. (Box 5, Folder 5)
    Reviews
  - Her Father: A Memoir (Boston: Faber & Faber, )., 1995 (Box 5, Folder 6-8)
    Copy edited manuscript
  - His Son (New York: W.W. Norton, )., 1981; 1980 (Box 5, Folder 9-10)
    T.D., final draft, 1980
  - Introduction [to Pushcart Prize XXV] (New York: W.W. Norton, )., 2001 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    Photocopy of proofs
  - The Little Magazine in America: A Modern Documentary History, edited by Elliott Anderson and Mary Kinzie (Yonkers, NY: Pushcart Press, ), 1979 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence, 1975-1981 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Ads and reviews (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Minutes of the Lead Pencil Club: Pulling the Plug on the Electronic Revolution, edited by Bill Henderson (Wainscott, NY: Pushcart Press, ), 1996 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Manuscript draft (Box 5, Folder 15-16)
    - Ads and reviews (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Pop [short story] T.D. ca., 1975 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - The Publish It Yourself Handbook: Literary Tradition and How-to, edited by Bill Henderson (Wainscott, NY: Pushcart Press, ), 1973 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Printer's manuscript (Box 5, Folder 19-22)
    - Ads and reviews, including an announcement for 1987 revised edition (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - The Search for Horatio Alger. T.D. ca., 1971 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Small Presses Today: A Continuing Vitality. T.D., 10 p. ca., 1975-1976 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Tower: Faith, Vertigo and Amateur Construction, (New York: Farrar, Straus, & Giroux), 2000 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Copy-edited manuscript (Box 5, Folder 26-27)
    - Correspondence, 1999-2000 (Box 5, Folder 28)
      Correspondence is with editors and readers at FSG; also individual letters from Doris Grumbach, Jan. 2, 1999, George Plimpton, Jan. 4, 2000, and others.
    - Reviews (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - A Tradition of Do It Yourself Publishing. (Box 5, Folder 30)
    Draft manuscript, heavily revised throughout. 30 p.
- Additions, 2007
  - Pushcart Press Printed, 2006 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Pushcart Prize XXXI nominations (Box 6, Folder 2-4)
  - Simple Gifts (New York: Free Press, 2006). (Box 6, Folder 5-7)
    First draft manuscript, 2001; reviews.